Finding aid to the Department of Astronomy Records CA.MS.00072
Smith College Archives
Department of Astronomy records
1847-1996
Smith College Archives
Smith College. Dept. of Astronomy.
CA.MS.00072
6.458 linear feet (16 containers)
The collection contains papers related to the Smith College Astronomy Department. Founded in 1887 with the building of a new observatory and with Mary E. Byrd as Director, it became part of the Five College Astronomy Department starting in 1960. Records include a history of the department, booklets, course and faculty information, diagrams, account books, notebooks and photographs of astronomical observations, information on observatory instruments, correspondence, and notes and photographs of astronomical societies. Student work is also included, as well as information on the Five College Program.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Office Files
II. Student Work
III. Five College Program
IV. Observatory Records
V. Societies
Biographical / Historical
The first mention of astronomy being taught at Smith College was in the first College Circular in 1872, where it is listed as a study for the upper classes. In 1878, the circulars named William C. Esty as the Astronomy Professor. Esty was a professor at Amherst College who came to Smith for three hours a week in the fall term. In 1881, Esty was replaced by Professor David P. Todd, another Amherst professor who taught limited courses at Smith.
In the 1885-1886 school year, two trustees gave funds to erect a new observatory and purchase astronomical instruments. A plaque on the new building read "This observatory with its apparatus is a tribute of affection to Henrietta Chapin Seelye and Sarah Tappan Williston by their husbands A.D. 1886." The observatiory had a steel moveable dome, a telescope with a glass 12 inches in diameter, transit instruments, chronometer, clock, and other astronomical instruments selected by Todd.
In 1887, Smith hired Mary E. Byrd as Teacher of Astronomy and the Director of the Observatory. Also in 1887, the Astronomy Department started offering courses in all three semesters and took on two graduate students, Bessie and Laura Gill. Byrd was known as a strong willed woman, and she retired in 1906 after a fight with the administration over the college's acceptance of money from Andrew Carnegie and John D. Rockefeller, which she found reprehensible. During her time at Smith, Byrd wrote several manuals on teaching astronomy at the colligiate level using the laboratory model and pioneered a method of determining cometary positions by photography.
In 1906, Byrd was suceeded by her assistant Harriet W. Bigelow ('93), who was primarily interested in comets. When Bigelow started, she had one or two assistants, but when Marion LeRoy Burton came on as president in 1910 he changed course requirements so that every student had to take courses in a mathematical science. Enrollment in astronomy courses went up to 400, so the Astronomy Departement grew to five. In 1927, students were no longer required to take both biological and mathematical sciences, and the department shrank to two faculty. In 1934, Bigelow died suddenly on sabatical in Java. Marjorie Williams, who had been Assistant Professor since 1925, took over for Bigelow until she retired in 1956.
The Five College Astronomy Department (FCAD), was founded in 1960 as a collaborative arrangement between the Astronomy Departments of Amherst, Mount Holyoke, and Smith Colleges plus the University of Massachusetts Amherst. Hampshire College was added to the group after its creation in 1970. The first major collective research initiative was the Five College Radio Astronomy Observatory, begun in 1970. The original meter-wave telescope was replaced by the world's largest millimeter-wave telescope, which is still in use in 2019.
As of 2019, the Astronomy Department is now made up of four faculty members, with research interests in the formation of stars within molecular clouds, galaxy formation and evolution, and ultra-faint radio sources. The department offers a major and minor in astronomy, as well as a minor in astrophysics. It is still part of the FCAD.
Scope and Contents
Records include a history of the department, booklets, course and faculty information, diagrams, account books, notebooks and photographs of astronomical observations, information on observatory instruments, correspondence, and notes and photographs of astronomical societies. Student work is also included, as well as information on the Five College Program.
Astronomy--Study and teaching (Higher)--Massachusetts; Astronomy--Study and teaching (Higher)--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Smith College. Dept. of Astronomy.; Smith College--History--Sources.; Smith College. Astronomy Club; Smith College Astronomical Society.
- SERIES I. OFFICE FILES
  Scope and Contents
  SERIES I. OFFICE FILES consists of background information on the program of studies, account books, correspondence and course information.
  - Sciences: General, 1951-1996; undated (Box 1223, Folder 1)
  - History of Science Studies Program of Studies, 1983-84 (Box 1223, Folder 2)
  - Astronomy
    - General, 1939-1993; undated (Box 1223, Folder 3)
    - Account book, 1898-1934 (Box 1223, Folder 4)
    - Budget sheets, 1911-1933 (Box 1223, Folder 5)
    - Code, 1939; undated (Box 1223, Folder 6)
    - Conferences, 1929-1938 (Box 1223, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1885-1947; undated (Box 1223, Folder 8-9)
    - Courses, 1934-1986
      - 11-37b (Box 1223, Folder 10)
      - 101-237 (Box 1223, Folder 11)
      - 100-110 (Box 1223, Folder 12)
    - Astronomy Department
      - Reports, 1888-1904 (Box 1224, Folder 1)
      - Annual Reports, 1906-09 (Box 1224, Folder 2)
      - Reports and minutes, 1919-1920 (Box 1224, Folder 3)
      - Secretary's book, 1919-1920 (Box 1224, Folder 4)
- SERIES II. STUDENT WORK
  SERIES II. STUDENT WORK consists of rules, models and diagrams of observations, photographs and charts of eclipses and student notebooks.
  - Rules, models and diagrams, 1902-05 (Box 1225, Folder 1)
  - Comets: Telegrams re: observations, 1939-1954 (Box 1225, Folder 2)
  - Eclipses: Photographs and charts, 6/13/17; 5/14/38; 11/7/38 (Box 1225, Folder 3)
  - Five observation notebooks, 1905-1915 (Box 1225)
  - Eleven comet observation computer books, 1902-1930 (Box 1226)
- SERIES III. FIVE COLLEGE PROGRAM
  SERIES III. FIVE COLLEGE PROGRAM consists of faculty lists, Four-College Astronomy Department information, information on laboratory work, examinations, observatory visitor books, photographs and course notebooks.
  - Course notebooks
    - Astronomy 11, 1930 (Box 1227)
    - Astronomy 10b (teaching course), 1913 (Box 1227)
    - Astronomy 22, 1924-25 (Box 1227)
    - Astronomy 8a, 1906-08 (Box 1227)
    - Astronomy (general), 1915 (Box 1227)
    - Astronomy, Special Honors, 1928-1930 (Box 1227)
  - Smith College Observatory Notices, 1955; 1973 (Box 1228, Folder 1)
  - Five-college observatory radio telescope, 1976 (Box 1228, Folder 2)
  - Faculty list, undated (Box 1228, Folder 3)
  - Four-College
    - Astronomy Department, 1953-1965 (Box 1228, Folder 4-5)
    - Graduate program, 1962-64 (Box 1228, Folder 6)
    - Faculty, 1959 (Box 1228, Folder 7)
    - Observatory in Whately, 1962-1974 (Box 1228, Folder 8)
    - General, 1935-1966 (Box 1228, Folder 9)
    - Gifts and grants, 1958 (Box 1228, Folder 10)
    - Laboratory work, undated (Box 1228, Folder 11)
    - Library, 1931-1948; undated (Box 1228, Folder 12)
    - Examinations, 1912-1939 (Box 1228, Folder 13)
    - National Science Foundation, 1961-67 (Box 1228, Folder 14)
- SERIES IV. OBSERVATORY RECORDS
  SERIES IV. OBSERVATORY RECORDS consists mostly of notebooks on charts and plates, mean and apparent star places, radial velocity, variable stars, the Meridian Circle, sunspots and transit instrument observations, but also contains correspondence and information on observatory instruments.
  - Observatory visitor book, 1955-58 (Box 1229)
  - Open house, 1933-1956 (Box 1229, Folder 1)
  - Order book, 1896-1933 (Box 1229, Folder 2)
  - Smith College Observatory Notices, 1977-1981 (Box 1229, Folder 3)
  - Parties, 1977 (Box 1229, Folder 4)
  - Photographs
    - Classes, 1890s-1900s; 1930s (Box 1229, Folder 5-6)
    - Solar eclipse, April 7, 1940 (Box 1229, Folder 7)
  - Telescopes, 1990-92 (Box 1229, Folder 8)
  - Meridian Circle observations, seven notebooks, 1894-1904 (Box 1230)
  - Meridian Circle reductions, four notebooks, 1888-1957 (Box 1230)
  - Correspondence, 1885-86 (Box 1231, Folder 1)
  - Equipment, 1888-1957 (Box 1231, Folder 2)
  - Instruments
    - Camera, 1936 (Box 1231, Folder 3)
    - Chronograph, 1887-1904 (Box 1231, Folder 4)
    - Chronometer, 1934-1947 (Box 1231, Folder 5)
    - Clock, 1887-89; 1960 (Box 1231, Folder 6)
    - Field glasses, 1893-1908 (Box 1231, Folder 7)
    - Gaertner measuring machine, 1943 (Box 1231, Folder 8)
    - Levels, 1888-1903; 1945 (Box 1231, Folder 9)
    - Micrometer, 1888-1907 (Box 1231, Folder 10)
    - Photographic reflectors, 1847 (Box 1231, Folder 11)
    - Telescopes, 1885-1920; 1957-59 (Box 1231, Folder 12)
      - Gaertner, 6", 1910-11 (Box 1231, Folder 13)
      - Portable, 1890-1909; 1937 (Box 1231, Folder 14)
      - Information, 1885; 1979 (Box 1231, Folder 15)
    - Observatory, position, 1900-1914 (Box 1231, Folder 16)
  - Schedule book, 1901; 1906-07 (Box 1232, Folder 1)
  - Science building, 1945; undated (Box 1232, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks: star observations, 1893-1906; 1911 (Box 1232, Folder 3)
  - Notebooks (Box 1232, Folder 4)
    - charts and plates, 1918 (Box 1232)
    - mean and Apparent star places, 1905-1916 (Box 1232)
  - Marjorie Williams
    - Radial velocities, 1929; 1936-39 (Box 1232, Folder 5)
    - Variable stars
      - Correspondence, 1934-1946 (Box 1232, Folder 6)
      - Photographs, 1900; 1904; undated (Box 1232, Folder 7)
      - Field 8, 1930-38; undated (Box 1232, Folder 8)
      - Field 8 plots, undated (Box 1232, Folder 9)
  - Notebooks: Meridian Circle observations books I-III, 1887-1894 (Box 1233)
  - Notes: Meridian stones, lines, marks and gnomons, 1901 (Box 1233, Folder 1)
  - Notebooks (Box 1234)
    - Sunspot observations books I-II, 1908-1945 (Box 1234)
    - Sunspot observations books III-IV, 1945-1953 (Box 1234)
    - AAVSU sunspot observations, 1945-1951 (Box 1234)
    - Equatorial telescope observations books I-IV, 1891-1931 (Box 1234)
  - Sky photographic observations
    - 3" telescope, 1933-1978 (Box 1235, Folder 1-2)
    - 11" telescope, 1930-1977 (Box 1235, Folder 3-4)
  - Notebooks: Transit instrument observations, books I-VIII, 1904-08 (Box 1236)
- SERIES V. SOCIETIES
  SERIES V. SOCIETIES consists of information, photographs, records, notes and predictions of the American Association of Variable Star Observers (AAVSO), the Astronomy Club, Smith College Astronomical Society, Students for the Exploration and Development of Space and Telescopium.
  - American Association of Variable Star Observers
    - Photos, records, notes and predictions, 1929-1952 (Box 1237, Folder 1)
    - Memos, correspondence and notes, 1976 (Box 1237, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, 1920-1950; undated (Box 1237, Folder 3-4)
  - Astronomy Club: Charter, 1955 (Box 1237, Folder 5)
  - Smith College Astronomical Society
    - Annual letter, 1900-1923 (Box 1237, Folder 6)
    - Constitution (Box 1237, Folder 7)
    - Records, 1891-1921 (Box 1237, Folder 8)
  - Students for the Exploration and Development of Space, 1993 (Box 1237, Folder 9)
  - Telescopium
    - Meeting notes, questionnaire, 1913-1938 (Box 1237.1)
    - Minutes, 1899-1940 (Box 1237.1)
    - Telescopium and Astronomical Society (visitor and graduate name book), 1907-1954 (Box 1237.1)